[Music]
England is one of the four nations that
make up the modern United Kingdom
alongside Wales Scotland and Northern
Ireland being by far the largest in
terms of land mass and population
England has for centuries been the most
powerful and developed Nation within the
British Isles having exerted its
influence over its immediate neighbors
through economic and Military
might however it may come as a surprise
to know that for much of its early
history England itself was influenced by
many other neighboring cultures and
languages from as far back as
prehistoric times England has played
host to successive waves of migration
and Conquest which over the subsequent
Millennia and centuries
have coalesced into a unique mixture of
language culture and Heritage that is
unlike anywhere else in the world but
how did this relatively small nation go
on to mold not only the future Destiny
of the British Isles but also shape much
of the modern world in which we live
today this is the history of
England the nation of England has been
shaped by countless political upheavals
Wars and invasions over the past several
Centuries with perhaps the most iconic
and defining of these being World War II
we all know that the Allies were
ultimately Victorious however if youve
ever wondered how this conflict could
have played out differently you can now
Envision this for yourself by playing
Call of War who have kindly sponsored
this video you can fight up to 100 other
players in this free-to-play online
realtime PVP strategy game that can take
weeks to fully complete which is great
if you're a fan of long-term strategic
based games like we are you can recruit
many different units to build out your
army including tanks planes and the
nuclear bomb as well as Forge alliances
with other players as part of your
chosen Grand strategy call of War can be
played on both PC and mobile with the
same account and if you sign up with a
link in the video description you'll
receive an exclusive gift of 13,000 gold
and one month premium subscription for
free this offer is only available for 30
days after this video goes live so don't
miss out the land that would one day
become the nation of England looked very
different to the first humans who
settled there during the prehistoric
Stone Age back then the wider British
Isles weren't even Islands at all but
were instead connected to Continental
Europe by a land bridge as the last
glacial period came to an end around
11,000 years ago the melting ice sheets
caused the sea levels to rise which
subsequently flooded the low-lying land
bridge called doggerland thereby
permanently cutting Britain off from
Europe despite being separated from the
Continental Mainland communication and
cultural exchanges continued to occur
between the peoples of Europe and those
inhabiting what would eventually become
England the practice of farming which
originated in the Middle East was
introduced around 4,000 BC and the first
permanent settlements which possessed
Monumental tombs and ceremonial Stone
circles such as Stonehenge were also so
built around this time as the Stone Age
turned into the Bronze Age England for
the most part remained alike to the rest
of Britain and indeed the rest of Europe
similar cultural and linguistic
practices were introduced as a result of
successive waves of migration from the
continent which eventually morphed into
the Celtic culture which had become
widespread over much of Western Europe
by the 12th century
BC life for the Celtic peoples of
England continued in much the same way
for the next several Cent centuries that
was until the year 55 BC when an
invasion Force unlike any seen before
landed on the southern coast the Roman
Republic which would soon become the
Roman Empire was the uncontested
superpower of the ancient world having
expanded across the Mediterranean as
well as more recently further northwards
into what is now modern France the Roman
general who had led the recent conquest
of what was then termed ghoul was none
other than Julius Caesar whose Ambitions
soon turned to Conquering the the lands
across the English Channel Caesar's
initial Invasion achieved little more
than Landing his army on the coast and
so a second largest scale Invasion
followed the next year in 54 BC this
Invasion saw Roman Legions Advance as
far as the Northern Bank of the river
temps despite this relative success the
Romans could not establish a permanent
foothold on the island during this time
and so withdrew back across the channel
the Romans nevertheless remained
convinced that the island could and
should be conquered and so almost a
century later the Roman Emperor Claudius
ordered that a properly planned and
maintained Invasion attempt be carried
out in the year 43 ad over the following
decades Rome's Legions Advanced across
the land and brought almost all of what
is now England under Roman rule founding
many settlements like London Chester and
York in the process although Rome's
Authority was occasionally challenged by
local revolts such as the one led by
Queen budika in 60 AD England remained
an integral part of the Roman Empire for
the next several centuries and had its
northernmost border fixed in place with
the construction of Hadrian's
Wall like all empires in history however
Rome's rise and fall was inevitable and
by the beginning of the fth century its
power and influence had been
significantly reduced the last Roman
Legions were withdrawn from England in
the year 407 to defend the more valuable
parts of the Empire on the continent
which were being threatened by numerous
migrating Barbarian tribes a handful of
these tribes soon turned their attention
towards England which set in motion a
series of events that would establish
and ultimately shape the very language
culture and history of the English
people these Germanic tribes
collectively referred to in history as
the Anglo saxin first migrated to
England sometime during the 4th Century
probably serving as mercenaries in the
Roman army however by the mid fifth
century a significant number of these
peoples had settled in the Eastern
portion of the country the precise
nature of this process is still a matter
of debate amongst historians with some
advocating for a large scale Invasion
and violent displacement of the Native
Celtic population While others argue for
a more peaceful and gradual process of
acculturation in either case the
Anglo-Saxons replace the Romano British
language culture and people with their
own Germanic customs and ways of life
the language that they introduced would
one day evolve into the English language
that we speak today although the
Anglo-Saxons were United in tongue
culture and religion they were
politically separate having established
their own independent kingdoms across
the land by the 7th Century the native
Britains had withdrawn themselves to the
Far Western parts of the island such as
Wales and Cornwall leaving the seven
Anglo-Saxon Petty kingdoms of East Ang
Anglia Essex Kent Sussex meria North
Umbria and Wessex to form the basis of a
distinct but as yet disunited English
Nation over time the Anglo-Saxons
converted from their old Germanic Pagan
beliefs to Christianity and set about
consolidating power for themselves Often
by fighting one another as well as the
neighboring British kingdoms to the west
and PS to the north by the late 8th
Century the feuding Anglo-Saxons had
Amalgamated into four larger kingdoms
North Umbria meria East Anglia and
Wessex however the very survival of
anglo-saxon England would soon be called
into question when fleets of longboats
suddenly began to appear off the
coastline in the late 8th Century the
Viking age in England is widely attested
to have begun with the well documented
raid on the North umbrian Monastery of
lindes fan in the year
793 although other smaller raids had
been carried out in England before this
time as well as in other parts of the
British Isles what began as sporadic
attacks on isolated treasure Laden
monasteries continued well into the
following Century but in the year
865 however the Vikings adopted a change
in strategy from Hit and Run raiding to
one of conquest and occupation late that
year a vast Viking Army landed in
southeast England with the intention of
taking the land of the four Anglo-Saxon
kingdoms for themselves this great
heathen Army as the Anglo-Saxon
Chronicle referred to the Viking Force
first marched northwards and took
control of the kingdom of North Umbria
in 867 followed by East Anglia in 869
and then meria in 874 leaving only the
kingdom of wessix as the last
independent Anglo-Saxon
Kingdom led by King Alfred wesix had
thus far evaded the marauding Vikings
either by fighting them in battle or
paying them off however by 878 the
Vikings had overrun the greater parts of
wessix and forced Alfred into hiding
with the threat to his kingdom and the
future of England hanging in the balance
King Alfred was able to muster an army
for a last stand against the Vikings at
the Battle of Edington in May of that
year ultimately proving Victorious King
Alfred earned himself the epithet of the
Great by successfully driving the
Vikings back eastwards to the lands
which remained under their own rule of
Dane law with Anglo-Saxon do now
restored the kings of wesex gradually
began to reconquer the remaining English
lands under Viking occupation Alfred's
grandson ethelon successfully conquered
the kingdom of York in 927 and adopted
the title King of the English for the
first time the emergence of a now
unified and Powerful Kingdom of England
greatly alarmed the neighboring rulers
within the British is who subsequently
formed an alliance of Vikings and Scots
to challenge ethon's dominance in the in
the year
934 the resulting Battle of brunen bur
one of the most decisive ever fought in
the history of the British Isles saw
ethon's Army win the day and secure the
independence and supremacy of England
which was to last for the best part of a
century by the dawning of the New
Millennium however England's Kings had
become complacent and the threat posed
by marauding Danish Vikings had
reemerged over the following decades the
Throne of England passed between
Anglo-Saxon and danish rulers and at one
point the kingdom was ruled as part of
the wider Scandinavian North Sea empire
under King gut by the year 1042 the
house of wesix had been restored to the
throne under King Edward the Confessor
however his failure to produce an air
meant the future of England was once
again thrown into question by numerous
competing claims to be his
successor when Edward died in 1066 the
powerful English nobleman Harold
godwinson took to the throne much to the
outrage of Duke William of Normandy King
Harold had Radder of Norway and King
Swain II of Denmark who all asserted
claims to the throne themselves the
events of the year 1066 would
undoubtedly be the most pivotal in
English History and would irreversibly
change the very Fabric and nature of the
country the Battle of Stanford Bridge
fought in September of that year saw
King Harold godwinson defeat an invasion
Force led by his Norwegian counterpart
however just a few weeks later his
exhausted Army was forced to make a long
rapid March South to face another
Invasion Force led by dukee William the
Battle of Hastings which was fought on
the 14th of October 1066 is perhaps the
most infamous date in English history
with King Harold being killed in action
supposedly by taking an arrow to the eye
the end result was the extinguishment of
the Anglo-Saxon line of Kings and its
replacement with the new Norman French
Dynasty which was established by William
who had himself crowned as the new king
of England on Christmas day of that
year the Norman Conquest brought about a
profound change to the governance of
England after fighting off countless
English revolts and asserting dominance
over the neighboring Kingdoms in Wales
and Scotland King William I commissioned
the Doomsday Book to survey the land
people and monetary value of his kingdom
the completed work showed that
practically the entire Anglo-Saxon
nobility had been replaced with Normans
who had introduced French as the
language of the ruling aristocratic
Elite from this point onwards England's
future would be irrevocably intertwined
with that of France as many of England's
Lords now also held feudal lands across
the channel the Norman Dynasty lasted
only about 80 years in England when yet
another succession crisis triggered open
civil war between Henry First's
legitimate successor Empress Matilda and
the favored candidate chosen by the
nobility Steven of blis the result was
that Steven ruled as king until his
death in 1154 and was to be succeeded by
Matilda's son Henry II as a descendant
of both the noble houses of Normandy and
plantagenet as well as through a
subsequent marriage to Elanor of
aquatain Henry II ruled not only over
England and parts of Wales and Ireland
but also over an enormous sthe of
Western France under what would later be
termed the Anin
Empire England was ruled by the
plantagenet Kings for most of the
medieval period but experienced a great
deal of mixed fortunes the late 12th
century through the mid- 13th centuries
for example was marked by calamities and
political turmoil as their territories
on the continent were greatly reduced
owing to conflict with the kingdom of
France the resulting Fallout amongst the
powerful English Barons led to a uction
in the king's absolute power with the
signing of Magna cataa in 1215 by King
John despite these measures civil war
between the king and the Barons
continued throughout much of the century
and only came to an end with the
accession of king Edward the first to
the throne in
1272 Edward strengthened the power of
His government with the opening of the
first Parliament and significantly
expanded the English influence within
the British Isles by conquering Wales
and attempting to do the same same to
Scotland as the 14th century dawned
England continued to engage in
expansionist wars with its neighbors
particularly against France which began
the long and protracted series of
conflicts collectively referred to as
the Hundred Years War during the reign
of king Edward III England achieved
great success at the battles of pry and
poier however military actions soon came
to a halt as an altogether different and
more deadly enemy was about to land on
England's Shores the black death which
originated in Asia and spread throughout
Europe during the second half of the
1340s arrived in England aboard a ship
that had sailed from English controlled
gany in
1348 within less than 2 years the plague
had spread over the entire country and
is estimated to have killed as much as
half of the
population not only did this reduce the
Manpower for England's armies but it
also led to dramatic socioeconomic
change changes within the country itself
the surviving peasantry faced ever
increasing taxes to pay for the costly
Wars and were not being paid high enough
wages for their labor which was now in
even greater demand these tensions
eventually boiled over into the peasants
Revolt of 1381 which saw widespread
disturbances across the country but were
most concentrated in the Southeast where
Rebels marched on London and killed many
government officials whom they blamed
for causing their grievances
order was eventually restored but the
situation in England remained volatile
the unpopular King Richard II was
deposed in 1399 by his cousin who became
King Henry IV further crises and revolts
plagued his Reign but they were
successfully put down largely due to the
military actions of his son and
successor Henry V who ascended the
throne in
1413 under King Henry V England
witnessed some of the most most defining
events in its history such as the
renewal of the Hundred Years War with
France and the stunning Victory gained
at the Battle of aenor in 1415 which
thereafter became enshrined in English
Legend however Henry's untimely death in
1422 initiated a reversal in England's
fortunes his infant son Henry V 6
inherited the throne but his Reign was
marked by overall defeats of France in
the ongoing conflict culminating in the
English being driven out of virtually
the entire territory by
1453 Henry the 6 position worsened in
the following years with discontent
among the feuding nobility sparking
another civil war in
1455 named the wars of the Roses in
reference to the emblems of the two
branches of the plantagenet dynasty the
white rose of York and the red rose of
Lancaster the fighting continued
radically for the next 30 years until
Henry chuda the last last surviving male
of the lancastrian line returned from
Exile in France and defeated the yorkist
King Richard III at the Battle of
Bosworth field in
1485 England then transitioned into a
period of relative peace owing to the
houses of Lancaster and York uniting
under King Henry II's marriage to
Elizabeth of York which ushered in the
establishment of the chuda dynasty the
war ravaged economy was gradually
rebuilt and the enlightened idea which
had emerged during the Renaissance in
Italy made their way into English
society when Henry viith died in 1509 he
was succeeded by his son Henry VII whose
Reign started off promisingly but later
descended into tyranny and became one of
the most disruptive in all of English
History this was largely caused by his
desire for a male Heir his first
marriage to Catherine of aragan produced
only one surviving daughter Mary after
his grounds for divorce for rejected by
the pope Henry decided to split England
away from the Catholic church and
establish his own Protestant Church of
England this caused a great deal of
religious upheaval within the country
and would later give rise to a period of
sectarianism which would last for the
best part of 100 years Henry's
subsequent marriages and hopes for a
series of male successes fared little
better his second wife and berin was
executed after producing only one
daughter named Elizabeth his third third
wife Jane Seymour died from
complications after giving birth to a
son named Edward his fourth marriage to
an of cleaves ended in divorce his fifth
wife Katherine Howard was executed for
being unfaithful and his sixth and final
wife Katherine par was the only one to
survive with her reputation and head
intact owing to Henry himself dying in
1547 succeeded by his only son Edward v
6 England became radically more
Protestant under his rule although it
was to be shortlived for Edward died of
tuberculosis in
1553 he was in turn succeeded by his
Half Sister Mary who was married to King
Philip II of Spain and was a devout
Catholic Mary's reign as Queen witnessed
the fall of the last English outpost on
the continent C to the French in 1558
but her Reign was mostly defined by
attempts to reverse the recent
Protestant Reformation in England by
severely persecuting
any adherence to the faith some 280
people were burned at the stake under
her oppressive rule earning her the
epithet of Bloody Mary despite being
married she too failed to produce an
heir and so upon her death in 1558 the
Throne of England passed to her half
sister
Elizabeth under Queen Elizabeth the
England entered a golden age of
prosperity the Protestant Church of
England was reestablished and some
degree of religious tolerance was GR
granted towards Catholics the
instruments of the state were greatly
strengthened through new laws and proper
Administration which consequently led to
the population of the country growing
significantly reaching some 5 million
people by the early 17th century
Elizabeth and England also saw an
increase in the art and literature with
the likes of William Shakespeare
producing some of the nation's most
famous works and plays which remained
popular to this very day there was also
a significant upshift in England's
economic and accompanying military might
during this time largely brought about
by the expansion of English commercial
interests in the Americas and Asia
figures such as Sir Walter rally and Sir
Francis Drake pioneered England's
emergence as a powerful Maritime Nation
leading expeditions to newly discovered
parts of the world and successfully
defending England in its most desperate
hour of need against the Spanish Armada
in
1588 nevertheless Elizabeth the died
childless in 16003 and so the throne
passed to her closest male Protestant
relative King James I 6 of Scotland of
the House of Stewart who subsequently
became King James I of England through
the union of the
crowns despite being the king of both
Nations and ruling over virtually the
entire island of Britain the two
kingdoms remained separate from one
another James's early Reign faced many
challenges the most notable being the
Gunpowder Plot of 16005 which saw
discontent English Catholics attempts to
blow up the king during the state
opening of parliament it was also during
this time that the first permanent
English colonies were established in
places like America and India which
would go on to form the basis for the
British Empire in centuries to come the
latter part of King James's Reign was
marked by increasing tensions with
Parliament over governance of the
country these issues however would come
to a dramatic head during the reign of
his son Charles
I disagreements over power religious
Affairs and governance within the
kingdom coupled with King Charles I's
refusal to cooperate with Parliament led
to Growing discontent between the two
centers of power in England eventually
in 1642 armed conflicts broke out with
the English Civil War being fought
between the forces loyal to the king
called royalists and the parliamentarian
forces called Roundheads
pitched battles such as those fought at
Edge Hill Maron Moore and nby were
pivotal in determining the war's outcome
which ultimately ended in Victory for
the parliamentarian New Model Army under
the leadership of Oliver Cromwell for
his role in allowing the country to
descend into a chaotic state of Civil
War King Charles I was executed in 1649
and England briefly became a republic
with Cromwell as its
leader the monarchy was eventually
restored in 1660 however with King
Charles II returning to London albeit
with his power significantly reduced the
country was still in a fragile state
after the Civil War and two events which
struck London in the mid 1660s the Great
Plague of 1665 and the great fire of
1666 did great damage to the nation's
capital Charles II's Reign ended with
his death in 1685 and was succeeded by
his brother James II
however this quickly ignited another
political Ferrari within the kingdom
owing to James being a devout Catholic
and rumors that he wished for England to
return to the old Faith various
political factions quickly pressed for
his Protestant daughter Mary and her
Dutch husband Prince William of Orange
to replace him in what became known as
the Glorious
Revolution William landed with an
invasion force on England's South Coast
in November 1688 but did not wish to
seek an open battle believing that James
II's regime would collapse on its own
this duly happened and James fled to
France leaving the throne vacant for
William and Mary to assume the role of
king and queen under joint
rule despite James's seeming abdication
he did have some support in Ireland and
so decided to launch a military campaign
there with the hope of restoring him to
the throne James was nevertheless
defeated by the forces of King William
III in battle and was forced to flee to
France once again the continuation of
the Catholic House of Stewart in Exile
however would continue to threaten
England's political establishment well
into the next
Century England returned to relative
peace under the rule of William and Mary
for they both accepted the Bill of
Rights in 1689 which significantly
reduced the power of the crown by
recognizing the authority and
sovereignty of parliament during the
reign of Queen Anne who inherited the
throne from her sister Mary the English
and Scottish parliaments were formerly
merged into one thereby creating the
Parliament and Kingdom of Great Britain
through the acts of Union in
1707 Queen Anne was the last of the
Stewart Dynasty to sit on the throne and
owing to a recently introduced law that
allowed only Protestants to become
Regent upon her death the crown passed
to her distant second cousin the German
Prince George of
Hanover from that point onwards the
history of England would no longer be
that of a separate Sovereign Nation but
rather that of one of the four nations
that made up the United Kingdom England
and for that matter Britain under the
hanovarian kings of the 18th century
transitioned into becoming a modern
nation state growing Commerce and
mercantilism propelled the country into
becoming the leading Global Maritime
power of the age which was backed up by
the military might of the royal Navy on
the high seas Britain's colonies also
increased in importance during this time
however the loss of America during the
war of independence significantly
damaged the country's prestige on the
world stage the only real domestic
threat to the nation was posed by the
descendants of the exiled House of
Stewart Living in France who
unsuccessfully attempted to overthrow
the British government and Georgian
monarchy on two separate occasions in
what became known as the Jacoby
rebellions of 1715 and 1745
the 19th century would see Britain
become the pre-eminent global superpower
of the age thanks to the Innovations
introduced by the Industrial Revolution
these accelerated the nation's economic
output and allowed for further expansion
of the British Empire it would become
the largest to have ever existed in the
history of the world although the
defining events of the following 20th
century namely the first and second
world wars would virtually bankrupt the
nation and initiate the beginning of the
end for Britain's dominance as a world
power the past 2,000 years of history
have undoubtedly left their mark on the
Modern English Nation with its people
being made up of the descendants of the
various groups who arrived on its Shores
over the centuries although the impacts
of these events May no longer be all
that visible to the modern eye their
legacy is perhaps more noticeable in the
Modern English language that we speak
today whether it be the words borrowed
from Latin introduced by the Romans the
Germanic of the Anglo-Saxons the Old
Norse of the Vikings or the French of
the Normans England's language is a
result of the constant Evolution and
adaptability of its speakers which is
perhaps why it has become the most
spoken language in the world
today many thanks again to call of War
who have sponsored this video this free
online PVP World War II strategy game
allows you to engage Eng in epic battles
and take over the world click the link
in the video description to get 13,000
gold and 1 month of Premium subscription
for free and fight your way to Victory